Okay, now Ben just showed you the single
leg RDL with the landmine. And now he's
going to show you guys the reverse
lunge.
I want to go over three ways to do
landmine reverse lunges. I'm going to
start with the easiest version first and
progress to the hardest version at the
end of the video. So, where I usually
start people is standing perpendicular
to the landline. You're going to stand
so that the edge of the bar is right in
line with the inside leg. Bend down.
Grab the bar with the thumb over the
bar. Not choking up like this right
here. Thumb over. Come up. And then put
that arm out to the side. Create a tight
fist to get everything tight in here and
stable. Then you're going to keep that
chest up nice and tall. Step back. Big
long lunge. And come forward. Back and
forward. So here the the bar is coming
back, but it's also arcing in a little
bit to help get this muscle firing to
keep everything stable. So for clients
that get a little sloppy with lunges and
wobble all over the place, it cleans it
up almost immediately. So that's where I
would start is standing perpendicular.
You want to make sure not to stand too
much this way because then when the bar
arcs, it'll hit the knee. But you also
don't want to be too far this way
because then it's harder to hold the
weight at the top. So instead, right in
line with that front leg, hand just goes
where the back leg would be, fill that
gap, and come forward. If you notice
with this ver with this version, I'm
able to step back a lot farther than I
could with a choosing a dumbbell or a
kettle bell. So, for that reason, I use
this a lot with people that are trying
to target their glutes and also people
with knee pain because you're able to
keep more of a vertical shin. If you
notice, I I can keep a completely
vertical tibia, whereas that's nearly
impossible with dumbbells or kettle
bells. So, if you do have uh knee pain
yourself or you're a trainer and your
client has knee pain, this is a really
good variation to allow people to do
lunges. It's also good if you're
somebody that's trying to target the
butt a little bit more than the quad.
So, the next way that we would do it is
we would go facing the land. So, here,
same thing applies as the perpendicular
version. Bar right in line with your
legs. I'm going to grab the end of the
bar, hand out to the
side, and just like that. Leg goes
straight back. So, if you think about
what's happening here, the bar is arcing
slightly back. So, it's actually a much
more hip dominant punch than you would
get from a barbell or a kettle bell or
dumbbell. In fact, I can actually go all
the way back to an egg chair angle.
Whereas, if you're trying to do that
with a kettle bell or a dumbbell, it
would be damn near impossible to get
back up. So the the barrier functions
both as a load and as a counterbalance
action. So for people that just
struggle
there, this allows you to keep this
vertical shin stress more on the hips
and glutes and less less strain on the
knee for people with knee issues. Uh
similar to that but slightly more
challenging would be the front loading
version. So here, getting in and out of
position is actually probably the the
most tricky part of the exercise. So I'm
very nimble about it. You're going to
pick the bar up, but the way to get the
load up, especially when it's heavier,
this weight's not heavy for me, so I can
just pick it up with one hand. What when
the weight were heavier, uh it would be
too hard to do that. Also, I don't want
to hurt my back. So the way I'm going to
pick it up is go like this. squat
straight down and then just kind of
explosively pick the weight up and catch
it on my chest. What people tend to do
here when they hold the bar, uh, several
several problems, people try to put
their hands like this
and that causes the shoulders to torque
and the hips because everything's
connected. So, it's very
important that your hands are stacked on
top of each other. You can either
interlock your fingers like this or
overlap, but you definitely don't want
to do this because that causes
everything to twist. So, first thing is
establishing that good position. Also,
the bar wants to be right on your chest.
You'll often get people that set up with
the bar here. That's a ton of strain on
the arms and it also doesn't put you in
a good position at the bottom of the
lunge. So, the best way to establish a
good position at the bottom is to nail
this uh the top position properly. What
that looks like is bar right on your
chest here. You're going to lunge back
and forward. This is slightly more e-
dominant than holding the bar here. So,
it's a little bit more emphasis on the
quad,
uh but still works the glutes as well.
So, here you're going to go like this.
This is challenging even with lighter
loads and it's also a really good
anterior core exercise. So th those are
the three ways.
Perpendicular facing like this and front
loaded. Give all three a try and see
which one you like best.